A Guide to the Papers of Francis Scott Key, 1821-1841
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of Francis Scott Key 1821-1841
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
6949-a
10 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was acquired through deposits by Clifton Waller Barrett on December 17, 1963 and January 26, 1965. The items were changed to gifts on July 1, 1991.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of 10 items, chiefly correspondence and manuscripts of Francis Scott Key.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in two series. Series I contains manuscripts, and Series II contains letters.
Contents List
- Series I: Manuscripts
  - Poem to Sarah Gayle: "If life's pleasures cheer thee ..." 1833 Dec, AMsS, 1p.
    Page from the album of Sarah Gayle with autograph verse by Francis Scott Key, Sarah Gayle is the nine-year-old daughter of John Gayle, Governor of Alabama and his wife, Sarah.
  - Poem by Francis Scott Key 1833 Dec 13, AMsS, 6p.
    Extract from Miss Koonegay's album containing poem by Mrs. Sarah Gayle to Francis Scott Key and his poem in reply, extract from Mrs. Gayle's journal concerning the poems.
  - Poem by Francis Scott Key 1833, AMsS, 2p.
    Poem to Miss Sarah Gayle beginning "Thine hand fair little maiden! ..."
  - Poem by Francis Scott Key 1834 Dec 6, AMs, 2p.
    Poem begins "Cheek of rosier hue ...," Octavia Walton mentioned in last line may have been recipient.
  - Poem by Francis Scott Key n.d., AMs, 2p.
    begins "Dear Isabella! could our grief ...," a lament over the death of a woman, Isabella's virtues and charms are set forth at some length.
- Series II: Letters
  - Francis Scott Key to Rev. Joseph R. Andrus 1821 Aug 22, ALS, 3p.
    Key sends letter by Lieutenant Stockton to Rev. Andrus in Africa relative to the colonization in Africa (eventually Liberia). Both "Rev. Andrus" and "Rev. Joseph Andrews" are written on address side and both are found in books on Liberia.
  - Francis Scott Key to J. Davis 1824 Jan 13, ALS, 2p.
    Key advises Davis that his fee for the case just completed is $100, includes J. Davis' reply in which J. Davis sends the money and gives information on another case for which he wants representation by Francis Scott Key, J. Davis' reply on back.
  - Francis Scott Key to [?]. 1835 Jan 21, ALS, 1p.
    Key writes concerning the recipient of the letter who was rejected by the Senate for an appointment, indicates that he expects Roger Taney's appointment also to be rejected.
  - Francis Scott Key to Dr. J. K. Mitchell 1841 Sep 25, ALS, 2p.
    Key writes regarding proposed publication of volume he would like to write on criminal law, includes an outline of the proposed contents, asks Dr. J. K. Mitchell to make inquiries of publishers regarding acceptability of such a volume.
  - Francis Scott Key to Ann Phoebe Key n.d., Friday, ALS, 2p.
    Key writes from Montgomery Court House that he has brought his girls to Miss Judge's school, gives information about this Quaker school.